<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Matthew Nolan's Blog]]></title><description><![CDATA[Matthew Nolan's Blog]]></description><link>https://matthewnolan.xyz</link><image><url>https://matthewnolan.xyz/icon.png</url><title>Matthew Nolan&apos;s Blog</title><link>https://matthewnolan.xyz</link></image><generator>RSS for Node</generator><lastBuildDate>Mon, 26 Dec 2022 14:27:50 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://matthewnolan.xyz/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 01 Oct 2020 04:00:00 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[2022 Matthew Nolan]]></copyright><language><![CDATA[en]]></language><managingEditor><![CDATA[support@menlo.one]]></managingEditor><webMaster><![CDATA[support@menlo.one]]></webMaster><ttl>60</ttl><item><title><![CDATA[Secret DAO Voting on Ethereum with Timber Network]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>In Brief:</p>
<ul>
<li>Some colleagues and I are developing a new cross-chain messaging relayer we call <a href="https://github.com/timbernetwork">Timber Network</a>. </li>
<li>We used it for a prototype which lets Ethereum DAOs vote secretly (video demo below).</li>
<li>Our prototype <a href="https://twitter.com/sozuhaus/status/1600305757353701377">won hackathon sponsored by BitDao</a>, of which we are extremely honored.</li>
<li>🌳🌐</li>
</ul>
<h1 id="applicationspecificcrosschainmessaging">Application Specific Cross-Chain Messaging</h1>
<p>I wanted to share a little info on a project I've been working on with some colleagues. We're building a network which allows different distinct blockchains to communicate and interact with one another. We call it <a href="https://github.com/timbernetwork">Timber Network</a>. Timber stands for Trustless Incentivized Messaging Blockchain Encrypted Relayer.</p>
<p>The <a href="https://jumpcrypto.com/security-stack-up-how-bridges-compare/">first generation of this sort of technology, the "bridges"</a>, were  comprised of a trusted third parties which simply moved tokens from ChainA to ChainB, several having some high profile security issues. Then came the 2nd generation, the "relayers" which are much harder in terms of security. Some introduced features for "generalized" cross-chain message relaying. This feature could be very useful though it's primary use for token transfers in and out of liquidity pools ie "bridging".</p>
<p>While some of these generalized messaging relayers are extremely cool, they all seem to focus on "general messaging" as its primary use was token transfers. I see a need for a next generation, relayers which execute more complex logic: an "application specific" relayer. The concept is that dApps that share common dApp primitives (ie voting, minting nfts, swaps) agree on a standardized set of messaging protocols which would allow distinct blockchains to work interoperably. The goal is to connect blockchains together and leverage one another’s features like legos.</p>
<h1 id="introducingtimbernetwork">Introducing Timber Network</h1>
<p>Timber Network has three primary components: a base blockchain which manages governance, gateway smart contract deployed on supported chains, and relayers which are responsible for interacting with gateway smart contracts. Privacy is preserved using <a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2022/06/15/using_snarks.html">ZK-SNARKs</a> between the relayer and base chain. The base chain enforces trust minimization in the network while allowing modularity in the from the contracts and relayer.</p>
<h1 id="workingexamplesecretballotdaovotingforethereum">Working Example: Secret Ballot DAO Voting for Ethereum</h1>
<p><strong>Problem:</strong> The Ethereum network is public by design which is usually great but bad for DAOs who want a secret ballot (since anyone can see how you voted). Secret ballots are sort of an <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Secret_ballot">MVP feature of democracy</a> which isn't possible on Ethereum alone. This is actually a growing problem as teams increasingly form DAOs to operate their startup (voting against your team or boss might lead to some awkward situations).</p>
<p>There are other blockchains which have privacy features, one of our favorites being <a href="https://scrt.network/">The Secret Network</a>. But it's difficult for a DAO to simply pack up and migrate to an entirely different blockchain because the DAO might have voting tokens which they cannot bridge, a locked treasury, or using ENS for their identity. With an "application specific" cross-chain relayer, the DAO can balance the strengths and weakness of multiple chains together such as keeping their voting tokens on Ethereum but using the privacy of Secret Network to vote.</p>
<p><strong>Solution:</strong> To demonstrate this we built a prototype which balances both networks. We have contracts deployed to both Secret and Ethereum and a relayer with limited permissions on each. Upon voting the relayer provides Secret with the only data points it needs to know: a signed message with their ETH address, voting token balance, and chain metadata which registers the user to vote on Secret.</p>
<p><div className="text-center embed-container">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/xgD8ouIV50M" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer;  clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>
<small>In this video I demonstrate an Ethereum DAO user secret ballot voting by using Timber Network to leverage the privacy features of Secret Network without having migrate their tokens off Ethereum.</small>
</p>
<p>What is known is that a user is registered but not what they voted for. At the end of the proposal only the result is sent back to Ethereum where it would be possible to then call another contract such as a treasury contract. All execution is trustless, votes are private, and the relayer only has permissions to read and write these specific data.</p>
<h1 id="furtherplans">Further Plans</h1>
<p>This DAO use case is just one example of the potential possibilities of using blockchains in this way. There are endless possibilities when connecting these networking like this. Our long term vision is a blockchain equivalent of <a href="https://zapier.com/">Zapier</a>. As a developer this is what I want:</p>
<ul>
<li>I want a private, encrypted, front run resistant order book on <code>Oasis</code> to trigger transactions on <code>Ethereum</code> <code>Uniswap</code></li>
<li>I want members of my DAO on <code>Ethereum</code> to vote on a political party privately on <code>Secret Network</code> with their <code>Ethereum</code> voting tokens, and then give those who voted access to my politics group on <code>Lens Protocol</code></li>
<li>I want to <code>mint an NFT</code> on <code>BSC</code> only to users who own a <code>Bored Ape</code> on <code>Ethereum</code></li>
<li>I want users to be able to stake their <code>Solana</code> NFTs to validate on <code>Cosmos</code></li>
<li>I want users to add liquidity to my token on <code>Uniswap</code> on <code>Ethereum</code> and then <code>bridge</code> their LP token over to my yield farm on <code>Avalanche</code></li>
<li>I want to build an epic Web3 game where the top PFP NFTs from <code>Ethereum</code> <code>BSC</code> and <code>Avalanche</code> battle one another in a fierce metaverse dance off for yield rewards on <code>Moonbeam</code></li>
</ul>
<p>And I want all of that to happen in a way which is trustless, verifiable, private when it needs to be, and without making a single Web2 API call.  </p>
<h1 id="finalthoughts">Final Thoughts</h1>
<p>Timber Network is under heavy development and there is still a lot of work to be done. If you're interested in working with us, please reach out on twitter or email.</p>
<p>Team Timber would also like to give thanks to <a href="https://www.bitdao.io/">BitDAO</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/sozuhaus">Sozu House</a> for their support on this project.</p>]]></description><link>https://matthewnolan.xyz/blog/secret-dao-voting-ethereum-with-timber-network</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://matthewnolan.xyz/blog/secret-dao-voting-ethereum-with-timber-network</guid><category><![CDATA[TED]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matthew Nolan]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 10:33:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[TED Talk and Residency]]></title><description><![CDATA[<p>I’m very honored to have been accepted into the Spring 2017 TED Residency class. The TED Residency an in-house incubator for breakthrough ideas. Residents spend four months in the TED office with fellow brilliant minds who are creatively taking on projects that are making significant changes in their communities, across many different fields. At the end of their session, Residents have the opportunity to give a TED Talk about their ideas. <a href="https://blog.ted.com/meet-the-spring-2017-class-of-ted-residents/">More info here</a>.</p>
<div className="text-center embed-container">
    <iframe width="560" height="315" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/M-SE6Fm6PGU" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe>
</div>
<p><a href="https://youtu.be/M-SE6Fm6PGU">Link to my TED talk on YouTube</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.ted.com/talks/matthew_nolan_world_peace_one_swipe_at_a_time">Link to my TED talk on TED</a></p>
<p><a href="https://www.ted.com/profiles/2943657">Link to my TED profile</a></p>]]></description><link>https://matthewnolan.xyz/blog/ted-talk</link><guid isPermaLink="true">https://matthewnolan.xyz/blog/ted-talk</guid><category><![CDATA[TED]]></category><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matthew Nolan]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 25 Oct 2020 17:28:42 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>